chapter-1:
  qa1:
    context: 'Archaeology is the study of past societies through analysis of
  what people left behind. Archeologists dig up and examine
  artifacts—objects made by humans. Artifacts may be tools, weapons,
  art, and even buildings made by early humans.'
    question: 'What human made objects do Archaeologists study?'
    answer: 'artifacts'

  qa2:
    context: 'For decades, scientists assumed these earliest of upright creatures must also
  have used tools. In 1974, Donald Johanson challenged this theory when his team
  found a new skeleton in Ethiopia. Johanson nicknamed the female skeleton “Lucy”
  and suggested that she was the common ancestor for several types of early human
  life. Scientists called this type of hominid Australopithecus (aw•STRAY•loh•PIH•
  thuh•CUS), or “southern ape.” It flourished in eastern and southern Africa.'
    question: 'What type of hominid did Donald Johnason and his team find in Ethiopia?'
    answer: 'Australopithecus'

  qa3:
    context: 'The end of the last Ice Age, around 8000 b.c., was followed by what is called the Neolithic Revolution—that is, the revolution
  that occurred in the Neolithic Age, the period of human history from 8000 to 4000 b.c. The word Neolithic is Greek for “new stone.”
  The name New Stone Age, however, is somewhat misleading. The real change in the Neolithic Revolution was the shift from the
  hunting of animals and the gathering of food to the keeping of animals and the growing of food on a regular basis—what we call
  systematic agriculture.'
    question: 'What kind of agriculture is the keeping of animals and the growing of food on a regular basis?'
    answer: 'systematic agriculture'

  qa4:
    context: 'As a result of the steady food supply, people in Çatalhüyük had a food surplus.
  This meant people could enter other occupations than farming. Some people became artisans. These skilled workers
  made products such as weapons and jewelry and traded them with neighboring peoples. This exposed the people of Çatalhüyük to the wider world.'
    question: 'What was the name of the workers wo made products such as weapons and jewelry?'
    answer: 'artisans'

  qa5:
    context: 'Anthropology is the study of human life and culture. Culture includes what people wear, how they organize their society, and
  what they value. Anthropologists use artifacts and human fossils to create a picture of peoples’ everyday lives. Fossils are rocklike
  remains of biological organisms—a leaf imprint or a skeleton. '
    question: 'Which type of scientist uses fossils and artifacts to study early humans?'
    answer: 'Anthropologists'

  qa6:
    context: 'The second group descended from Homo sapiens is Homo sapiens sapiens, meaning
  “wise, wise human.” These are the first to have an anatomy similar to people today. 
  Physical evidence suggests that Homo sapiens sapiens appeared in Africa between
  150,000 and 200,000 years ago. They probably spread out of Africa to other parts of the world about 100,000 years ago, replacing
  populations of earlier hominids in Europe and Asia. This is referred to as the “out-of-Africa” theory (or replacement theory).'
    question: 'Which hominids do scientists believe were probably the first to spread out of Africa?'
    answer: 'Homo sapiens sapiens'

  qa7:
    context: 'Because Paleolithic people were hunters and gatherers, they had to follow animal
  migrations and vegetation cycles. Paleolithic humans were nomads—people who move from place to place to survive.
  Archaeologists and anthropologists think these nomads probably lived in small
  groups of twenty or thirty. Hunting depended on careful observation of animal
  behavior patterns and demanded group cooperation for success.'
    question: 'What did Paleolithic people have to do to survive?'
    answer: 'follow animal migrations'

  qa8:
    context: 'Early humans were able to sustain themselves through the use of stone tools. To make such tools, early people used very
  hard stones, such as flint. They used one stone to chip away parts of another, creating an edge. Hand axes of various kinds—
  pointed tools with one or more cutting edges—were the most common. Hand axes
  eventually were set in wooden handles, making them easier to use. By attaching
  wooden poles to spear points and hardening the tips in fire, humans created spears to kill large animals'
    question: 'Which invention allowed humans to hunt large animals?'
    answer: 'spears'

  qa9:
    context: 'The first civilizations developed in river valleys where people could carry on the
  large-scale farming that was needed to feed a large population. As farming became
  abundant, more people would live in the city. New patterns of living soon emerged.'
    question: 'Where did the first civilizations develop?' 
    answer: 'river valleys'

  qa10:
    context: 'By 5000 b.c., farmers in Southeast Asia were growing rice. From there, rice farming spread into southern China. By 6000
  b.c., farming millet and domesticating dogs and pigs seem to have been established in northern China. In the Western
  Hemisphere, Mesoamericans grew beans, squash, and maize. They also domesticated dogs and fowl in this period between 7000 and 5000 b.c'
    question: 'Who were people in the western Hemisphere growing beans, squash, and maize in 7000 b.c.?'
    answer: 'Mesoamericans'


chapter-2:
  qa1:
    context: 'The most prominent building in a Sumerian city was the temple dedicated to the
  chief god or goddess of the city. This temple was often built atop a massive stepped tower called a ziggurat.'
    question: 'What is a Sumerian Stepped tower called?'
    answer: 'ziggurat'

  qa2:
    context: 'The Jews were monotheistic; they believed in one God called Yahweh
  (YAH•way), the Creator of the world and everything in it. In the Jews’ view, God
  ruled the world; all peoples were his servants, whether they knew it or not. God
  had created nature but was not in nature. The sun, the wind, and other natural phenomena were not gods, but God’s creations
  to be admired but not worshiped.'
    question: 'What is the belief in one God called?'
    answer: 'monotheistic'

  qa3:
    context: 'Egypt’s history begins around 3100 b.c., when King Menes (MEE•NEEZ) united
  Upper and Lower Egypt into a single kingdom and created the first royal dynasty. A dynasty is a family of rulers whose right to
  rule is passed on within the family'
    question: 'What is a family of rulers who pass on power within the family called?'
    answer: 'dynasty'

  qa4:
    context: 'Mesopotamian civilization refers to the achievements of people from three general areas: Assyria, Akkad, and Sumer. The
  Sumerians were the creators of the first Mesopotamian civilization.'
    question: 'Who created the first Mesopotamian civilization?'
    answer: 'Sumerians'

  qa5:
    context: 'To the north of the Sumerian city-states were the Akkadians (uh•KAY•dee•uhnz).
  They spoke a Semitic language. Around 2340 b.c., Sargon, leader of the Akkadians,
  overran the Sumerian city-states and set up the first empire in world history.'
    question: 'Which leader set up the first empire in world history?'
    answer: 'Sargon'

  qa6:
    context: 'The Sumerians created many inventions that still affect our lives today. Probably
  their greatest invention was their writing. In addition, historians credit them with
  many technological innovations.'
    question: 'What was the greatest Sumerian invention?'
    answer: 'writing'

